<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>People Related Articles on Developer Blog - Jacek Marchwicki</title>
    <link>/blog/people/</link>
    <description>Recent content in People Related Articles on Developer Blog - Jacek Marchwicki</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/blog/people/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Focusing external teams’ members to resolve business needs</title>
      <link>/blog/focusing-external-teams-members-to-resolve-business-needs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/focusing-external-teams-members-to-resolve-business-needs/</guid>
      <description>The article discusses the importance of focusing on business needs when collaborating with external teams. The author shares an example where an external engineer&amp;rsquo;s focus on perfecting code was hindering progress, and describes the steps taken to align the engineer&amp;rsquo;s focus with the project&amp;rsquo;s business needs. The outcome was improved productivity, better team behavior, and guidelines for more business-aware practices.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving App Stability: A Proactive Approach to Overcoming External Constraints</title>
      <link>/blog/improving-app-stability-a-proactive-approach-to-overcoming-external-constraints/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/improving-app-stability-a-proactive-approach-to-overcoming-external-constraints/</guid>
      <description>This article is about taking a proactive approach to improving app stability by addressing external constraints that can hinder development efforts. The author emphasizes the importance of specificity in identifying problems and using analytical tools to calculate the impact of those problems on business goals. The article provides a real-life example of how a team improved app stability within the constraints of external factors, such as an unstable backend server, by taking a creative and collaborative approach to problem-solving.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code Review - Team Agreements</title>
      <link>/blog/code-review-team-agreements/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/code-review-team-agreements/</guid>
      <description>Countless words have been written on why code review is good for the code of the app. But if during code review you focus solely on code, you’re doing it wrong.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Cooperation</title>
      <link>/blog/optimizing-cooperation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/optimizing-cooperation/</guid>
      <description>For developers, non-coding factors that are not directly related to their work are often a source of frustration. I’d like to show you that you have the power to make your company more efficient.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proposing architectural changes</title>
      <link>/blog/proposing-architectural-changes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/proposing-architectural-changes/</guid>
      <description>It’s not easy to introduce changes in a team that numbers more than just a few developers. You should ensure that everyone understands what is going to be changed, why and how. I’d like to guide you on how you can make this process as painless as possible.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Problem of Knowledge Sharing</title>
      <link>/blog/the-problem-of-knowledge-sharing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/the-problem-of-knowledge-sharing/</guid>
      <description>Many good articles mention the fact that modern business is based on knowledge sharing. Countless organizations implement systems that are supposed to make it easier. I’d like to follow this trend and show you my own, slightly different take on knowledge sharing, to help you optimize solutions within your environment.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t be fooled by knowledge shared in this self-development article</title>
      <link>/blog/dont-be-fooled-by-knowledge-shared-in-this-self-development-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/dont-be-fooled-by-knowledge-shared-in-this-self-development-article/</guid>
      <description>You shouldn&amp;rsquo;t trust this article and you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t trust me either. But you should still read this article if you don’t want to be lied to.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to introduce yourself to a new team</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-introduce-yourself-to-a-new-team/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/how-to-introduce-yourself-to-a-new-team/</guid>
      <description>When you join a new team, you usually want to show that you’re a valuable person to work with. You probably want to get settled in the team quickly, show what you&amp;rsquo;re made of, make new acquaintances and get something meaningful to do as soon as possible.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Story@Appunite</title>
      <link>/blog/my-story@appunite/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/my-story@appunite/</guid>
      <description>It was some time ago (2011), a year after I joined AppUnite as the first employee. At the time, I’ve just developed third iOS app (yes, this is no typo — iOS app :) ).</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
