<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Engineering Articles on Developer Blog - Jacek Marchwicki</title>
    <link>/blog/engineering/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Engineering Articles on Developer Blog - Jacek Marchwicki</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/blog/engineering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Analytical Metrics for Programmers: How NOT to Use Data to Improve Efficiency</title>
      <link>/blog/analytical-metrics-for-programmers-how-not-to-use-data-to-improve-efficiency/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/analytical-metrics-for-programmers-how-not-to-use-data-to-improve-efficiency/</guid>
      <description>Learn how to use analytics wisely to improve your software delivery process. This article will teach you the pitfalls of using metrics blindly and how to avoid them. Discover how to use metrics to identify and solve problems in your software development process.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When QA slows down your team</title>
      <link>/blog/when-qa-slows-down-your-team/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/when-qa-slows-down-your-team/</guid>
      <description>In my work, many a time have I witnessed QA offer less value than expected. I&amp;rsquo;ve gathered some thoughts to understand why it happened so many times, so that you might find ways to avoid it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When a product requirement is not worth implementing</title>
      <link>/blog/when-a-product-requirement-is-not-worth-implementing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/when-a-product-requirement-is-not-worth-implementing/</guid>
      <description>Life is full of compromises, so is software development - this article will help you make good decisions when an unforeseen problem occurs.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coastline paradox</title>
      <link>/blog/coastline-paradox/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/coastline-paradox/</guid>
      <description>The coastline paradox was first observed by Lewis Fry Richardson and later expanded upon by Benoit Mandelbrot in Science Magazine in 1967. It shows that measuring the coastline length is not as straightforward as it might seem.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Errors... oh... those errors</title>
      <link>/blog/errors...-oh...-those-errors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/errors...-oh...-those-errors/</guid>
      <description>In my opinion, good error handling is one of the most important features of an application.  But most people in development process ignore them.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Working with git submodules (very old article)</title>
      <link>/blog/working-with-git-submodules-very-old-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/working-with-git-submodules-very-old-article/</guid>
      <description>Working with submodules looks tricki at the beginning but it is an elegant way to share your project code and DRY (Don&amp;rsquo;t Repeat Yourself). We started to use submodules a lot in appunite.com, but there is not much said in WWW about how to use git submodules in real projects.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Working with gerrit (very old article)</title>
      <link>/blog/working-with-gerrit-very-old-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/working-with-gerrit-very-old-article/</guid>
      <description>As software engineers we want to improve our selves, we want to learn from mistakes of others, and we would like to improve our coding skills. This is why we&amp;rsquo;have decided to introduce a code review process, and for this we&amp;rsquo;ve chosen Gerrit tool.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
